Today we're going to, in one lecture, cover
an entire field, which is computational
complexity. It's sort of, it meets
algorithms in an interesting way, which is
algorithms is mostly about showing how
to solve problems well and showing that you
can solve a problem well. And computational
complexity is more about the lower bound
side, proving that you can't solve a
problem very well. You can't find a good
algorithm to solve it. We've seen a little
bit about lower bounds several lectures
ago, proving search and sorting lower
bounds in bounded branching decision tree
model. But these are much stronger notions
of badness. This is not about n versus n
log n, or constant versus log n. This is
about polynomial versus exponential, which
has been the sort of bread and butter
model in this class. Polynomial is a good
running time, and we're always striving
for that. Exponential is usually pretty
trivial to get. And so we're going to
talk about some different, they're called
complexity classes, that talk about this
issue and different ways to prove hardness.
This is a pretty high level lecture, so
you're not going to be expected to be able
to prove hardness. But you'll get a flavor
of what it's like. And this will segue
nicely into other follow on classes, which
is we're at pretty much the end of 006. So
natural to talk about what other things you
might study. One result we'll prove today
is that most problems actually have no
algorithm, which is kind of shocking, and
lots of other fun things. So let's get
started with the notion of p. This is a set
of all problems solvable
in polynomial time.
OK. So these are the problems that are
efficiently solvable. P is set of all of
them. And for contrast, exp is a set of
all problems solvable in exponential time.
Problems solvable in exponential time.
Exponential here means something like 2 to
the n to the constant. It's one reasonable
definition of exponential. So just the
exponentiation of this polynomial. So as
you might expect, every problem that we've
talked about in this class so far can be
solved in exponential time rather easily.
And algorithms, in some sense, is about
distinguishing these two, which problems
are in p versus are in, say, x minus p. So
to formalize this a little bit, I'm going
to draw a picture,
which is a bit of a simplification of
reality, but for the purposes of this class
will suffice and I think is a really
helpful way to think about things, which is
to have a big axis for a single axis for
how hard is your problem. What is the
difficulty of solving your problem? And
I want to be sure to leave. So the easiest
problems are always over here. And
each problem is a dot on this axis. Hardest
problems are way down the line. And I want
to make sure to leave enough space for all
the things I care about. So p, I'm just
going to call this segment up front. And
then I'm going to have a
bigger thing for exponential time.
So this is just to say that p is nested
inside x. Every problem that can be solved
in polynomial time can also be solved in
exponential time, because polynomial is
less than or equal to exponential. These
are just upper bounds. Being an x means
you're somewhere from this line to the
left. Being in p means you're somewhere
from this line to the left in terms of
difficulty. But formally, we would write p
is contained in x as sets. In fact, they're
also known to be different from each
other.
They can be solved in exponential time.
They cannot be solved in polynomial time.
For example, I'll
put that here. Sure.
For example, n by n chess
is in exponential time, but not polynomial
time. So what is the n by n chess problem?
This is I give you an n by n chess board.
And I describe to you a position. Here's
where all the white pieces are. Here's
where all the black pieces are. You can
have an arbitrary number of queens and
bishops and pawns of each color, of course,
up to n squared of them. They don't overlap
each other. And I want to know, does white
win from this position? Let's say it's
white to move. Can white win? And that
problem can be solved in exponential
time by exploring the entire tree of all
possible games. You can prove that it
cannot be solved in polynomial time. So
that's a nice example. A more positive
example, so to speak, is negative weight
cycle detection. It's literally
negative, but it's morally positive.
Negative weight cycle detection is the
following problem. I give you a graph, a
directed graph with weights. And I want to
know, does it have a negative weight cycle?
Yes or no? And this problem is in? P. P,
because we saw a polynomial time algorithm
for this. You run Bellman -Ford on an
augmented graph. So this is an example of a
problem we know how to solve. This whole
class is full of examples that we know how
to solve in polynomial time. But this
is a nice non -trivial and succinct one to
phrase. It's also an example of a decision
problem. A lot of, basically, all the
problems I'll talk about today are decision
problems, like we talked about last class,
meaning the answer is just yes or no. Can
white win from this position? Yes or no. Is
there a negative weight cycle? Yes or no.
Tetris we can also formulate as a problem.
This is a version of Tetris that you might
call perfect information Tetris. Suppose I
give you a Tetris board. It has some
garbage left over from your past playing,
or maybe it started that way. And I give
you the sequence of n pieces that are going
to come. And I want to know, can I survive
this sequence of n pieces? Can you place
each of these pieces as they fall such that
you never overflow the top of the board on
an n by n board? This problem can be solved
in exponential time. But we don't know
whether it can be
solved in polynomial time.
We will talk about that more in a moment.
It's a problem that very likely is not in
p, but we can't actually prove it yet. All
right. So there's one other class I want to
define at this point. And we'll get to a
fourth one also. But R is the class of all
problems that can be solved
in finite time. R stands for finite.
R stands for recursive, actually. This
is a notion by Church way back in the
foundations of computing. As we know,
we write recursive algorithms to solve
problems. In the beginning, that was the
only way to do it. Now we have other ways
with loops. But they're all effectively
recursion in the end. So R is all the
problems that can be solved in finite
time on any computer. So very general. This
should include everything we care about,
right? And it's bigger than x. It includes
problems that take double the exponential
time or whatever. So I will draw a
region for R. So everything includes
p. It includes exp. And so we also have
containment but not equal R. There's, of
course, many classes in between. You could
talk about problems that take double
exponential time. And that would have a
thing in between here. Or there's
also between p and exp. There's a lot of
different things. We will talk about one of
them. But before we get to the finer side
of things, let me talk in particular about
R. So we have a nice example, we being
computational complexity theory, or I
guess this usually just called theoretical
computer science, has a problem. And
if you're interested in this, you can take
604.
604. 1, I think? No, that doesn't sound
right. That's probability. It'll come to
me.
We have an explicit problem that is
not in R. So this class has been all about
problems that are in p. You have the
number? 6045. 6045. Thank you. It's so
close to this class. Or it's so close to
6046, which is the natural successor to
this class. So 6045
would talk about this.
So this class is all about problems that
are in p, which is very easy. But in fact,
there are problems
way out here beyond R.
And here is one such problem, which
we won't prove here today. It takes a whole
lecture to prove this.
Given a computer program,
does it ever halt?
Does
it ever terminate? This would be a
great thing if we knew how to solve. It's
basically an infinite loop detector. If
your problem doesn't halt, then it has an
infinite loop of some sort. And you'd like
to tell your user, hey, you have a bug in
your program. So this is one part of bug
detection. And it's impossible. There is no
algorithm that solves all inputs to this
problem. Maybe given one program that, say,
has zero lines of code, it could solve
that. It says, yeah, that one terminates.
And maybe you can detect simple kinds
of infinite loops. So there's some inputs,
some computer programs that you could
detect. But there's no one algorithm that
solves all inputs. This is kind of sad
news. We call such problems uncomputable.
It's just another word
for being not in R.
OK. And next thing I'd like to do is prove
to you that most decision problems are
uncomputable or
sketch -a -proof.
So remember, decision problems are problems
where the answer is just yes or no. This
is a very special kind of problem. And
even those, almost all of them, cannot be
solved. So halting is an example of a
problem we want, we can't solve. This whole
class, this 006, is about problems we
can solve. But today, I'm going to show you
that actually those are in the minority.
Most problems cannot be computed. This is
very strange and
also a little depressing.
So we'll talk more about that in a moment.
First, let me argue why this is the case.
So I'm going to be a little informal about
what exactly is a computer program and what
exactly is a decision problem. But roughly,
all I need to do, the only level of
precision I need is just to count how
many are there. What is a computer program?
Well, it's usually a file. What's a file?
It's like a string of characters. What's a
character? It's a string of bits. A program
is just, in the end, a string of bits,
finite string of bits.
We all understand that.
Whatever language you define,
in the end, every program is just a
string of bits. And a string of bits we can
translate into a number. So
we can convert between strings of bits and
numbers. When I say number, I mean what's
usually called a natural number or
a non -native integer. This is usually
represented by bold, board,
bold, blackboard, bold, capital
N. So this is just 0, 1, 2, and so on.
Now, what about
decision problems?
A decision problem is a specification of
what we want to solve. So we can think of
it as saying, for every input, is the
answer yes or no? That's literally what a
decision problem is. The only question is,
what is an input? And we've talked about
inputs and the size of inputs. And there's
lots of different ways to measure them. But
in the end, we can think of an input as a
string of bits also. It's just a file. So a
decision problem is a function
from inputs to yes or no.
And inputs, we're going to say,
well, that's string of bits, which we can
associate with a number in N. Here,
we can start to tie things together.
So in other words, a program is a finite
string of bits. And a problem is, in some
sense, an infinite string of bits, because
there are infinitely many possible inputs.
And for each of them, we specify
yes or no. So this is basically an infinite
string of bits.
So we can imagine 0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 0, 0, 0,
0, 1, 1, 1, 0, infinitely. For every string
of bits, we can say, OK, if your input is
the number 0, here's the answer, no. If
your input is the number 1, then the answer
is yes. If your input is the number 2,
your answer is yes, and so on down
this line. Every infinite string of bits
corresponds to exactly one decision
problem, which specifies for every possible
input integer, which corresponds to string
of bits, what is the answer, yes or no? So
this may seem subtle, or it may seem like
not a big deal. This is a finite string of
bits. This is an infinite string of bits.
But mathematics has well studied this
problem. And infinite strings of bits,
there are very many of them, infinitely
many. It's not surprising. There are also
infinitely many integers. So that maybe
doesn't seem that deep. But
there's a difference in infinitude. So if
programs and integers are countably
infinite,
infinite strings of bits are
what's called uncountable.
I think the most intuitive way to see this
is an infinite string of bits, if I put a
decimal or a binary point in front, this
encodes a real number between 0 and 1. So
this is roughly a real number in 0, 1. And
when I'm writing approximately equal here,
this really goes in both directions. Given
a decision problem, I can define a string
of bits, of course, giving me the answer
for all inputs. And I can convert that into
a real number between 0 and 1, but also
the other direction. If I take any real
number, that is a corresponding decision
problem. These are one to one by ejection
between them. And the bad news is
real numbers are uncountable. And natural
numbers are countable, which means there's
a lot more of these than there are these.
So one way you might
phrase this is informally,
is the number of natural numbers is way
smaller than the number of real numbers.
And so from that,
we derive that most problems are
unsolvable. Because every program solves
exactly one decision problem. We can also
run a program conceptually on all possible
inputs, and we will figure out what
function it's solving. And if we don't
allow random numbers in our program, which
I'm not here, then every program solves
exactly one decision problem. Possibly,
it's even worse for us, because multiple
programs probably solve the same decision
problem. They're just, they add irrelevant
lines of code, or they don't do anything
different. Or you run Bellman -Ford versus
running Bellman -Ford five times, you'll
get the same result. And that's actually
the bad direction for us. We'd like to
know whether there is a program that solves
every decision problem. And because there
are only this many programs and this many
decision problems, there aren't
enough to go around. So most,
what's the phrasing? Not nearly enough
programs for all problems. And so there's
no assignment.
Of programs to problems, because
there's just too many problems.
More money, more problems, I guess. So when
I first saw this result, I was shocked and
dismayed that why are we even doing
computer science if most problems can't be
solved? Luckily, it seems like most of
the problems we care about can be solved.
That's what this class is all about. And in
fact, even the problems that seem really,
really hard for us to solve, like n by
n chess, where we can prove it takes
exponential time, there is an algorithm to
solve chess. It's just really slow. This is
a statement about most problems can't even
be solved in finite time, no matter how
much time you give them. So it's not all
bad. Sort of luckily, most problems we care
about
are in R.
I don't know why. This is sort of a
mystery of life. But it's good news.
It's why we keep persevering and trying
to solve problems. With algorithms. Because
when we state problems, the statement tends
to be small? Well, I mean, so the question
was, maybe it's just because the short
statement problems are easy. But this is a
pretty short statement.
And it's hard. I think
I don't have a great reason why I wish
I understood. Is there's a general result
that if you have any question about the
program itself, then there's no algorithm
to solve it. Basically, any non -trivial
question about programs is hard. It's not
in R. And I guess if you took, I mean, if
you imagine taking a random statement of a
problem, then maybe this will be in the
middle of it with some probability. Maybe
that's why most. But this is a very strong
notion of most. There are so many more real
numbers than natural
numbers that I don't know.
All right.
I want to add one
more class to this picture.
Which is NP. It nestles in between P and
exp. So we know that P is contained in or
equal to NP. And NP is contained in or
equal to exp. We don't know whether there's
a quality here or here. Probably not. But
we can't prove it. But what is this class?
Couple of different ways to define it.
You might find one way or the other more
intuitive. They are equivalent. So as long
as you understand at least one of them,
it's good.
NP is just a class of decision problems. So
I defined P and exp and R arbitrary. They
could be problems with any kind of output.
But NP only makes sense for decision
problems. And it's going to
look almost like the definition of P,
problem solvable in polynomial time. We've
just restricted to decision problems. But
we're going to allow a strange kind of
computer or algorithm, which I like to call
a lucky algorithm.
And this is going to relate to the notion
of guessing that we talked about for the
last four lectures in dynamic programming.
With dynamic programming, we said, oh,
there are all these different choices I
could make. What's the right choice? I
don't know. So I'd like to make a guess.
And what that meant in terms of a real
algorithm is we tried all of the
possibilities and then took the max or the
or or whatever over
all those possibilities.
But what we were simulating is something
that I call a lucky algorithm, which can
make guesses and always makes the
right guess. This is a computer that is
impossible to buy. It would be great if you
could buy a computer that's lucky. But we
don't know how to
build such a computer.
So what does this mean? So informally,
it means your algorithm can make lucky
guesses. And it always makes the right
guess. And whereas in DP, we had to try all
the options and spend time for all of them,
the lucky algorithm only has to spend time
on the lucky guess, on the correct
guess. More formally, this is called a
nondeterministic
model of computation.
It should output yes or no. So like, say,
if you're exploring a maze, this algorithm
could say, should I go left or go right?
I'm going to guess whether to go left or go
right. And let's say it guesses left.
And so then it just goes left. And then it
reaches another junction and says, should
I go left or right? And it'll say, I'll
guess. And let's say I guess right this
time. And in the end, if I get to some dead
end maybe and I say no, or if I get to
the destination I'm trying to get to, I say
yes. So that's a nondeterministic
algorithm. And what does it mean to run
that algorithm? What does it mean for the
guesses to be lucky? Here's what it means.
These guesses are guaranteed, which way you
end up going, is guaranteed to lead you to
a yes if there is one.
If possible. So in my maze analogy, if my
destination is reachable from my source,
then I'm guaranteed whenever I guess left
or right, I will choose a path that leads
me to my destination. Whereas if the
destination is in some disconnected part of
the maze and I can't get there, then I
don't know what the guesses do. It doesn't
really matter because no matter what I
do, I'll end up in a dead end and say no.
That's the model. As long as you have an
algorithm that always outputs yes or no in
polynomial time, because we're only talking
about polynomial time lucky algorithms, if
there's any way to get to a yes, then
your machine will magically find it without
having to spend any time to make
these decisions. So it's a pretty magical
computer. And it's not a computer that
exists in real life. But it's a computer
that's great to program on. It's very
powerful. You could solve lots of things
with it. If you had this magical computer
that can guess whether it's yes or no, why
doesn't it just answer the question? Right.
So a nice check is, does this make all
problems trivial, all decision problems?
Maybe I should say, well, I don't know
whether the answer to the problem is yes or
no, so I'll just guess yes or no. This is
problematic because I might say it will
guess A or B. And if I choose the A option,
I will output yes. And if I choose the B
option, I will output no. In this model,
that algorithm will always output yes.
Because what it's saying is, if there's any
way to get to a yes answer, I will do that
way. And so such an algorithm that tries to
cheat and just guess the whole answer
to the problem will actually end up always
saying yes, which means it doesn't solve
a very interesting problem. It only solves
the problem which is represented by the
bit vector 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, where all
answers are yes. But good check. Yeah?
Does it have to be bound on the number of
things it has to choose between?
Yes. exponential number of?
Exponential number of choices is OK. I
usually like to think of it as you can only
guess one bit at a time. But we're allowed
polynomial time. So you're actually allowed
to guess polynomial number of bits.
And at that point, you can guess over an
exponential size space, but not more than
exponential. Cool. So it's polynomial time,
let's say, in the one -bit guessing model.
Did I say makes guesses? Let's add binary
here.
Otherwise, we get some
other class, which I don't want.
OK. Let's do a real example of such an
algorithm that's useful, which is Tetris.
So I claim Tetris is in NP
because there is a lucky algorithm, an
undeterministic polynomial time algorithm,
that can solve the Tetris game. So again,
you're given a board. You're given some
sequence of pieces. And you want to
know whether there's some way to place the
pieces that lets you survive. And so
what I'm going to do is for each piece,
I'm going to guess
how to place it.
So for the first piece, I'm going to guess
how far left or right do I move it. Then I
let it fall one step. Maybe I rotate it. I
choose a sequence of moves among left,
right, down, rotate right, rotate left.
And all along the way, I check is that move
valid. If the move is invalid at any point,
I just say return no. And then if the
piece gets nestled into a good spot, I
continue to the next piece. I do the same
thing, guess all the possible things I
could do to that. Again, I only need to
guess one bit at a time. And I'll only need
to do a polynomial number of guesses, like
a linear number of guesses for each
piece about where it falls in. So maybe a
quadratic number of guesses overall. And
then at the end, if I survived, oh, I also
have to check if a line clears. Then
I clear the line. And if in the end I
survive, I return yes. So this is a
nondeterministic algorithm. So I would say
check the rules of the
game. And if we survive,
return yes.
And if at any point we violate the rules,
for example, and go off the top of the
board, we return no. So this is an
algorithm that sometimes returns no and
sometimes return yes, depending on what
choices you make. And this model guarantees
if there's any way to get to a yes, it will
find it. If I swapped these answers, if I
returned yes when I violated the rules and
returned no if I survived, this would be an
uninteresting algorithm. Because it's very
easy to lose in Tetris. The hard part is to
survive. If I say, is there any way to play
the game in such a way that I violate the
rules, then of course the answer is yes.
You can just stack pieces and go off the
top. There's an asymmetry in this
definition of yes versus no. It always
finds yes answers if possible. It doesn't
always find no answers if possible. So it's
very important the way that I wrote these
questions. It's important that I define
Tetris as the problem of can I survive,
the problem of can I not survive. Is it
impossible to survive? That's a different
question. That problem is not in NP,
probably.
So slight subtlety there, yes versus no.
Let me give you the other definition of NP.
So if this one's confusing, which although
I prefer this definition, most people do
not. So this is confusing.
Let's do the other definition.
So other definition is that NP
is a set of decision problems
that can be checked
in polynomial time.
So if I have a solution, in some sense,
that can be checked for a yes example, if I
can represent my number as a subset sum of
a given set, it's easy for me to prove that
to you. And you can check it just by adding
up the numbers and checking that each
number was in the set. Whereas no
instances, I had an example of a target sum
that could not be reached. And the only
reason I knew that is because I had brute
forced the thing. And there's no succinct
way to prove to you that that number can't
be represented. A similar thing with
Tetris. What I would say is, so this is
version one. Version two
for Tetris is that a certificate
for a yes input
of Tetris is a sequence
of moves for the pieces.
If it's possible to survive in Tetris, I
can prove it to you. I can just play the
game and show you that I survived. No
answers, I don't know. It's hard to prove
to you that I can't survive a given
sequence of pieces. But yes, answers are
easy. I just show you, here's the sequence
of button presses I'll do for this piece,
then for this piece, then for this piece.
Notice, it's exactly the same thing that I
guessed in the beginning of this algorithm.
And then I did some other work to
implement the rules. And similarly, if I
gave you a certificate, which is the things
that I wanted to guess of how to play the
game, I can check this certificate by just
implementing the rules of Tetris and seeing
whether I survived. And if you violate the
rules at any point, you say no. And if
you survive, you return yes. That's what's
called a verification algorithm.
So let me formalize this notion.
Given a problem input
plus a certificate, like
that one over there,
there is a polynomial time. So this is yet
another definition. This is what I mean by
this definition of NP.
Verification algorithm
that satisfies two properties. One is for
every yes input, so every input where the
answer is yes to the problem,
there exists a certificate
such that the verifier says yes.
So this is saying it's possible to prove to
me that an answer is yes, because if you
ever have an input that the answer happens
to be yes, you can prove it to me by giving
me a certificate. There's always some
certificate that proves the answer is yes,
because the verifier, which runs in regular
polynomial time, this is a regular, old
fashioned, down to earth verification
algorithm, polynomial time in our usual
sense, it will say yes. And furthermore,
the yes answers from the verifier are
actually meaningful, because if I ever
give it a no input, it always says no, no
matter what
certificate I give it.
So this should really formalize what all
this means. It's equivalent to the previous
definition. This is saying that proofs
exist for yes instances. And this is saying
that proofs don't exist for no instances,
meaning there are no false proofs. So if
the verifier ever outputs yes, you know
that the answer to your problem is yes. But
if it outputs no, you're not sure. Maybe
you got the certificate wrong, because we
only know there's some certificate where
the verifier will say yes. Or maybe it was
a no input, and then it didn't matter
what certificate you used. But it's nice,
because it says on, say, Tetris, if I give
you the sequence of pieces, it's very easy
to write down a verifier which just
implements the rules of Tetris. And so then
you can at least check whether a solution
is valid in the yes case. You don't have
anything useful. So NP is a structure, some
additional structure, about the yes inputs
in your problem. And a lot of decision
problems are in NP. A lot of the problems
that we care about can be phrased as
an NP problem. As long as it's a decision
problem, usually answering yes or no
is provable, like subset sum, like Tetris.
These are all problems where if the answer
is yes, I can give you a convincing proof
why. And it turns out a lot of problems
fall into this NP setting. And so we have
some tools for talking about problems being
hard with respect to NP. Let me first talk
a little bit about P does not equal NP,
question mark. A lot of people conjecture
that P does not equal NP. It's sort of a
standard conjecture in theoretical computer
science. But we don't know how to prove
whether P equals NP or does not equal NP.
And so in this picture, I've drawn the
hypothesis, which is that NP is a strictly
bigger region than P is. But we don't
actually know whether there are problems in
this region. We don't know whether there
are problems in this region between NP and
x. We conjecture there are problems
here, and there are problems here. There's
definitely problems here or problems here,
but we don't know which one. Because we
know P does not equal x, but we don't
know whether P equals NP, and we don't know
whether NP equals x. If you could prove
that P does not equal NP, or disprove it,
you would win $1 million, which is not that
much money these days. But you would be
famous for the rest of time if you
could ever prove this. Every year, there's
usually a crackpot proof that it doesn't
work out. Some of them go to me. Please
don't send them. And anyway, it's a
very hard problem. It is sort of the core
problem in theoretical computer science,
how to prove P does not equal NP. But for
the most part, we just assume it. Now, what
does this conjecture mean? It essentially
means, the way I like to say it, is you
cannot engineer luck. Because NP problems
are problems you can solve by lucky
algorithms. P are problems you can solve by
regular old algorithms. And so if P
equal to NP, it means luck doesn't buy you
anything, which seems weird. Like, if I
can magically make these super powerful
guesses, then I can solve the problem.
That's NP. That seems super powerful, way
more powerful than regular algorithms,
where we have to actually brute force and
try all the choices. And so it seems pretty
solid that P does not equal NP. Of course,
we don't know how to prove it. Another
phrasing is that it's harder to come up
with proofs than it is to check them
from a mathematical perspective. This is
equivalent to P does not equal NP. So
that's why you should believe it. Now,
let's go over here.
The next notion is NP hardness.
So in particular, I want to claim, this is
a theorem that exists in the literature,
that if P does not equal
NP, then Tetris is not in P.
So I said right here, Tetris is in x, but
we don't know whether it's in P. But in
fact, we conjecture it's not in P, because
we conjecture that P does not equal NP. If
you could prove this conjecture,
and there's a lot of theorems that are
conditioned, assuming P does not equal NP,
then we get some nice results. Like, Tetris
cannot be solved in polynomial time. Cannot
figure out whether I can win a Tetris game
in polynomial time in the input size. Why?
This is a consequence of another theorem,
which is that
Tetris is NP -hard.
I'm going to define NP -hard informally
first, and then I'll define it slightly
more formally in a second. But this means,
roughly, that Tetris is as hard as all
problems in NP.
So let me draw
this in the picture.
So NP -hard is
this part.
Oh, did I leave myself
enough room? Maybe not.
Well, I'll squeeze it in. There's
another region here for x -part.
So your problem being in NP was a positive
result. It says you're no more difficult
than this line. You're either at this
position or to the left. Being in P was
also a positive statement. It says you're
here or to the left. Being in P is better
than being in NP, because this is a subset
of that. NP -hard is a lower bound. It says
you are at this point, this level of
difficulty, or to the right. And so it goes
from here off to infinity in difficulty.
And x -part says you're at least as hard as
the right extent of the x -set,
or you're harder than that, in a sense that
we will formalize in a moment. And this
place right here, as you might imagine, is
kind of interesting. It's exactly where NP
meets NP -hard. And this thing is called NP
-complete. You probably have heard about
NP -completeness, a famous notion. And this
is what it means. It is the problems that
are in NP. So they have a lucky algorithm
that solves them. They can be verified.
There are certificates that can be
verified. And they are NP -hard. So they're
in NP, and they are the hardest among
problems in NP. Now, they're not the
hardest problem. There are actually many
problems right here at this single level of
difficulty called NP -complete. Among them
is Tetris. There are many others, which I
will list in a moment.
So that is NP -completeness. So because
these problems are the hardest problems in
NP, if there's any problems here in between
in NP minus P, then these must be among
them. And so if you assume that P does not
equal NP, as most people do, then you know
that all problems at this rightmost extreme
of NP, the hardest of the problems in NP,
they must not be in P. And that's why I can
say if P does not equal NP, Tetris is not
NP. And also, any NP
-complete problem is not NP.
OK. What does as hard as mean?
This is our good
friend reductions.
We talk about reductions
a lot in this class.
Reductions are the easy way to use
algorithms. You just take your problem, and
we reduce it to a problem you already know
how to solve. You take the input to some
problem that you want to solve, and
you convert it into an input to some other
problem, like single -store shortest paths
or something like that, that you already
have an algorithm for solving. So if you
have an algorithm that solves problems for
problem B, you can convert
that into a solution for B.
And a reduction should also tell me how to,
given a solution to B, how to convert it
back into a solution for A. And when I say
solution here, I actually mean certificate
from over there.
So how, like, so if I, OK. So if I have, so
reduction consists of these two pieces,
how to convert an input to A to an input
for B, and given a solution to B, how to
convert it to a solution to A. Let me give
you some examples of reductions you've
already seen. You've seen a lot of them.
If I have unweighted shortest paths on the
left,
unweighted single -source shortest paths,
I can reduce that to weighted shortest
paths.
How? Set all the weights. Set all the
weights to 1. So here I'm given a graph
without weights. If I set all the weights
to 1, that turns it into an input for
weighted single -source shortest paths. So
if you didn't know how to solve this, you
could solve it by converting it. If you've
already written, say, a Dijkstra algorithm,
you could apply it to solve unweighted
single -source shortest paths. Now, we know
a faster way to solve this, but it's only a
log factor faster. And here we're talking
about polynomial versus exponential. OK.
So this is a valid reduction. It's not the
most interesting one from an algorithmic
standpoint, but it is an algorithm. Another
one we have. We've seen is if you
have integer weights on the left, you can
convert that to unweighted on the right
by positive integer weights by subdividing
each edge of weight w into w edges of no
weight. So that's maybe a little bit less
efficient. It depends what the sum of
the weights are. Another version that we've
seen is longest path in a graph. Weighted
path we can reduce to shortest path in a
graph weighted by
negating all the weights. We did this in
some of the dynamic programming things. Oh,
longest path in a DAG? We can convert
that into shortest path in a DAG just by
negating all the weights. So these are
all examples of converting one problem to
another. Usually, for algorithms, you
convert from a problem you want to solve
into a problem that you already know how to
solve. But it turns out this same tool of
reductions can give you negative results,
too. And in this case, we're going to
reduce from a problem that we think cannot
be solved and reduce it to the problem that
we're interested in solving. So let me
write more precisely what this means. If
you can find a reduction like this, it
means that solving A is at least as easy
as solving B.
Because I can solve A, in particular, by
converting it into B, solving B, and then
converting it back to a solution to A.
So in other words, if I can solve B, I can
solve A, which I can phrase informally as
A is at least as easy as B. And now using
grammar or contrapositive, whatever, this
is the same thing as saying that B is at
least as hard as A.
And this is what I mean by at least as hard
as. So this is my definition of at least
as hard in this notion of NP -hardness. So
what NP -hard means is that I'm at least as
hard as all problems in NP. And so what
that means is every problem in NP can be
reduced to Tetris, which is kind of funny.
But in particular, that means that if
there's an algorithm for Tetris, there's an
algorithm for all problems in NP. And so
that's actually the contrapositive of
this statement. So it's saying if there's a
polynomial, if I take the contrapositive
of this, this is saying if there's a
polynomial time algorithm for Tetris,
then P equals NP. There's a polynomial time
algorithm for every problem in NP. And the
way we prove that is by reductions. We take
an arbitrary problem in NP, and we reduce
it to Tetris. Luckily, that's not as hard
as it sounds, because it's already been
done once. There is already a reduction
from all problems in NP to singular
problems out there. The NP -complete
problems. There were some first NP
-complete problem, which I guess is Turing
machine. Non -determinant. It's basically
simulating lucky algorithms. So it's kind
of a not very interesting problem. But from
that problem, if you can reduce it to any
other problem, you know that problem is
NP -hard as well. And so briefly, I want to
show you some
examples of that here.
So I want to start out with a problem that
I'm just going to assume is NP -complete.
And it's called three partition. One
way to phrase it is I give you a bunch of
integers. I think I have it
written down over here.
Also, the board. I give you n integers. And
I'd like to divide them up into n over 3
groups of size 3, such that each group of
size 3 has the same sum. And it's written
there on the board. So you can also think
of this as the following. Problem, problem,
problem. I give you a bunch of rectangles
that are a side length or a bunch of
sticks, let's say, of varying lengths. And
I want to group them up like on the right
diagram. So in groups of three, such that
the total length of each group is exactly
the same. This is just a problem. And just
believe for now that it is NP -complete. I
won't prove that. But what I'd like to show
you is a reduction from this problem to
another problem. And that's jigsaw puzzles.
So you might think jigsaw puzzles are
really easy, and especially easy if I lose
the projector. But in fact, if you have a
jigsaw puzzle where some of the matches are
ambiguous, if there's multiple pieces that
could fit against a given tab or pocket,
then I claim I can represent this three
partition problem by building little sticks
like here. So if I want to represent a
stick of length ai, I'm just going to
build an ai. I didn't mention they're all
integers, and they're polynomial -sized
integers. I'm going to represent that by ai
different pieces here. And the red tabs and
pockets are designed to be unique, global
to the puzzle, like a regular jigsaw
puzzle. Given this piece on the left and
this tab on the right, there's a unique
pocket that fits perfectly into that piece.
So this joining is forced. And also this
joining is forced. But the blue tabs and
pockets are different. They're all the
same. They're all identical. And so if I
build this frame using the red unique
assignments, and I build these rectangles,
if I want to pack these rectangles into
this rectangle, that's exactly the three
partition problem, with some details that
I didn't fill in. But it turns out you'd be
forced to group these into groups of size
3, something like this, varying lengths.
OK, so that's an example of a reduction.
If you believe the three partition is NP
-hard, this proves to you that jigsaw
puzzles are NP -hard, something you may not
have known. Every time you solve a jigsaw
puzzle, you can feel good about yourself
now, especially if it has ambiguous mates.
Next is Tetris. So here is a reduction from
the same three partition problem, which is
one of my favorite problems, to Tetris. It
starts out with this strange board. It has
a bunch of columns here where I could put
pieces. So I'm not allowed to put pieces
in these dark regions. They all have height
t. t is the target sum that we want all of
the triples of numbers to add up to. And
there's n over 3 of these slots where I
can try to put pieces. And it's because of
this thing over on the right, there's no
way to clear lines in this game. And now to
represent a single number ai, I'm going
to give you this sequence of pieces, which
starts with an l piece. And then it has
ai repetitions of this pattern. And then it
ends with these two pieces. And so what
ends up happening is that this is in the
intended solution. You first place an l at
the bottom of one of these. And then you
repeat this pattern in this nice way.
And it fills up ai roughly height of this
bucket. And then at the end,
you have to put the i here.
And what this ends up guaranteeing is
that all of these pieces go into a single
bucket. You can check. It's tedious. But
if you tried to put some of these pieces in
one bucket and other pieces in a different
bucket, you would lose some space. And then
you would die. You have to put all these
pieces into one bucket. And so again, we're
just stacking rectangles. We're putting a
whole bunch of rectangles in one pocket,
and then a bunch of rectangles in another
pocket. We can switch back and forth
however we want. But the only way to win,
it turns out, is if you get all of those
rectangles to add up to exactly the right
height. Then you get a picture like this.
If you don't get a picture like this, you
can prove you end up dying. Then I'll give
you a bunch of l's. Then I'll finally give
you this t, which clears some lines. And
then I'll give you, it's the most
satisfying Tetris game ever. I'll give you
a ton of i's. And you get Tetris, Tetris,
Tetris. And you clear the entire board. And
so if you can solve the three partition
problem, you can clear the board and win
the game and be the best Tetris player
ever. And if there is no solution to three
partition, you're guaranteed to lose. And
so this proves Tetris is NP -hard. Cool. So
what else do I want to say
briefly? I think that's the main idea.
Another example, so this spot
is called x -completeness. And
this includes problems such as n by n
chess. So we know that chess requires
exponential time because, in fact, it's
among the hardest problems in exponential
time. But most common are the, somehow
because of the two -player nature of the
game, most common are NP -complete
problems. So a bunch of example NP
-complete problems I'll just briefly
mention here. So we saw the subset sum
problem, which we had a polynomial time
algorithm for, sorry, a pseudo polynomial
time algorithm for last class, in fact, has
no polynomial time algorithm, assuming p
equals NP. So pseudo poly is the best
you can hope for for subset sum. There's a
related notion called weakly NP -hardness,
which I won't get into here. Three
partition is one we saw. We saw some
reductions to other problems. So these are
all NP -complete. Longest common
subsequence is another dynamic programming
problem we saw with two sequences. I
mentioned you could solve it for three or
four or any constant number. But if I give
you n sequences, each of length n, that
problem is NP -hard, NP -complete. Longest
simple path in a graph, we know how to
solve longest path. You just solve shortest
path and negative weights. But longest
simple path, where you don't repeat
vertices, that's NP -complete. Relatedly,
one of the most famous NP -complete
problems is traveling salesman problem.
Finding the shortest path that visits all
vertices in a given graph. So instead of
just going from A to B, I want to visit all
the vertices in the graph. A lot of these
problems I'm phrasing as optimization
problems. But when I say NP -complete, I
actually mean a decision version of the
problem. For example, with this one, the
decision question is, is the shortest path
that visits all vertices in a graph less
than or equal to a given value x? If you
can solve this, then by binary search, you
can solve the overall weight. Three color
in your graph is hard, even though two
color in your graph is polynomial. Three
coloring is NP -complete. Assigning three
colors to the vertices so that no adjacent
vertices have the same color. Finding the
largest clique in a given graph, which
would be useful for analyzing social
networks, whatever. This is a fun one
for me as a geometer. If you're in a three
-dimensional world, which I am, and I
want to find the shortest path from here to
there that doesn't collide with any
obstacles, like this desk and all the
chairs and so on, in 3D, this problem
if you can fly, so if you're a drone flying
among all these obstacles, and you want to
find the shortest path from A to B, this is
NP -complete. Quite surprising. In two
dimensions, it's polynomial. You can reduce
it to graph shortest paths. But in 3D, it's
NP -hard. This is a formula problem that
comes up a lot. Given a Boolean formula
with and or not, can you ever make it true
if it has some variables that are not
assigned? And some more fun examples are
Minesweeper or Sudoku, basically any
paper and pencil puzzle you've ever played.
There's probably a paper out there proving
that it's NP -complete. And on the video
game side, Super Mario Brothers is NP
-hard. Legend of Zelda is NP -hard. Pokemon
is NP -hard. These problems are actually
all a little bit harder than NP in a
different class called PSPACE, which I
won't go into. But if you're interested in
this stuff, there is a whole class devoted
to it, which has online video lectures. So
you can watch them whenever you
want, called 6892, that gives a bunch of
especially fun examples of NP -hardness and
other types of hardness proofs from a sort
of algorithm's perspective for lots of
games and puzzles you might care about. And
that's it.